<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="mcconnell@osm.net">Stephen McConnell</author>
    <title>Component Development</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
  
    <section name="Overview">
    
      <p>
      In the earlier tutorials dealing with Transit Plugins we covered the general 
      subject of a deployment unit descriptor that associated an object instantiation 
      <tt>strategy</tt> with a <tt>classloader</tt> chain definition. The Metro platform 
      provides an alternative deployment strategy and runtime handler that delivers
      a complete context driven IOC object instantiation model. 
      </p>
      
      <p>
      In addition to instantiation there are several aspects of a class that 
      effect its deployment.  These aspects include thread-safety, a depoyment and 
      decommissioning lifecycle, garbage collection policy, etc.  Each of these concerns 
      are expresssed as well defined semantic features within the Metro component model.
      </p>

      <subsection name="Totorial Objective">
      
        <p>
        The objective of this tutorial is the demonstration of how we can 
        introduce a new instantiation strategy into a part deployment descriptor.
        Subsequent tutorials will use the resource established here as the baseline 
        for the introduction of the core Metro component model concepts.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        Supporting classes:
        </p>

        <table>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="hello/Demo.java.html">Demo.java</a></td>
            <td>A minimal component implementation.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><a href="hello/DemoTestCase.java.html">DemoTestCase.java</a></td>
            <td>Testcase that validates component deployment.</td>
          </tr>
        </table>

      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Component Creation">
      
        <p>
        The creation of a new component defintion is basically the same as the procedure
        used to creation a plugin.  In the following Depot project definition we are declaring 
        a new project with pablication of a jar and part artifacts.  The significant difference
        from a regular plugin is the usage of a custom part strategy.
        </p>
        
<source>
  &lt;project name="acme-demo-hello" basedir="hello"&gt;
    &lt;types&gt;
      &lt;type id="jar"/&gt;
      <font color="darkred">&lt;component xmlns="link:xsd:dpml/lang/dpml-component#1.0" 
         type="org.acme.Demo" 
         name="demo"/&gt;</font>
    &lt;/types&gt;
    &lt;dependencies&gt;
      &lt;test&gt;
        &lt;include ref="ant/ant-junit"/&gt;
        &lt;include ref="dpml/transit/dpml-transit-main"/&gt;
      &lt;/test&gt;
    &lt;/dependencies&gt;
  &lt;/project&gt;
</source>

        <p>
        The custom part definition introduced under the <tt>link:xsd:dpml/lang/dpml-component#1.0</tt>
        namespace is declaring the production of a new <tt>part</tt> datastructure under which 
        the class <tt>org.acme.Demo</tt> is to handled by the Metro runtime platform. The above 
        definition also includes the declaration of test phase dependencieswe will need to 
        launch the component.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        The generated part datastructure is show below (the custom Metro deployment 
        strategy is hilighted in red).
        </p>
        
<source>
&lt;part xmlns="link:xsd:dpml/lang/dpml-part#1.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"&gt;

  &lt;info/&gt;

  <font color="darkred">&lt;component xmlns="link:xsd:dpml/lang/dpml-component#1.0"
      type="org.acme.Demo"
      name="demo"
      collection="system"
      activation="system"&gt;
  &lt;/component&gt;</font>

  &lt;classpath&gt;
    &lt;private&gt;
      &lt;uri&gt;artifact:jar:org/acme/acme-demo-001#SNAPSHOT&lt;/uri&gt;
    &lt;/private&gt;
  &lt;/classpath&gt;

&lt;/part&gt;
</source>

      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Summary">
      
        <p>
        In this example the Demo implementation class contains nothing significant - 
        however, the important point of this initial tutorial is the association of
        a different runtime handler for the class within our part definition.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        The next tutorial extends the project
        with the introduction of <a href="context.html">context management</a> and 
        in particular, the way in which a component class declares context assumptions, 
        and the mechanisms used by the Metro runtime to fullfill those requirements.
        </p>
        
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Related Links">
        
        <ul>
          <li><a href="../resources/plugins.html">Transit Plugin Tutorial</a></li>
          <li><a href="http://www.dpml.net/metro">Metro Component Management System</a></li>
          <li><a href="http://www.dpml.net/metro/concepts/ioc.html">IOC Overview</a></li>
          <li><a href="http://www.dpml.net/metro/concepts/context.html">Context Awareness</a></li>
        </ul>
        
      </subsection>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>



