<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="mcconnell@osm.net">Stephen McConnell</author>
    <title>Component Development Strategies</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Depot Application Management">

      <p>
      The Depot product is an application management system that 
      we will be using in the OSM tutorials.  Depot comes preconfigured with 
      the Transit resource managment system and a set of services that will 
      handle the automatic installation of the Magic build system (used extensivly
      throught the tutorials), and the Metro component management platform.  The 
      core set of products we will be dealing with include the following 
      <a href="http://www.dpml.net">DPML</a> solution.
      </p>

      <table>
        <tr><th>System</th><th>Description</th></tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Depot @DEPOT-PRODUCT-VERSION@</td>
          <td>
        Depot is a utility used in the management of applications.  It provides
        support for product installation, Transit preference management, application
        deployment and server activation.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Transit @TRANSIT-PRODUCT-VERSION@</td>
          <td>
        Transit is a small resource managmenet system based on the JVM URL
        Handler architecture.  It provides support for the retrieval and caching 
        of resources and service supporting plugin deployment.  Transit is 
        included as a part of the Depot distribution.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Magic @MAGIC-PRODUCT-VERSION@</td>
          <td>
        Magic is an antlib that provides support for transitive dependencies
        across projects.  Magic is used daily in the management of 100s of 
        interdependent projects within DPML and is a foundation tool in dealing with
        highly complexity applications and the automation of component meta data 
        generation.  Installation of Magic can be executed via Depot as required.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Metro @METRO-PRODUCT-VERSION@</td>
          <td>
        Metro is a state-of-the-art component management platform that delivers
        complete support for Inversion of Control, componet assembly, dynamic
        component management, and complete plug-and-play semantics.  Installation 
        of Magic can be executed via Depot as required.
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>


    </section >

    <section name="Binary Downloads">

      <subsection name="License">

      <p>
        All products listed here are developed under open-source by the <a href="http://www.dpml.net">
        Digital Product Meta Library</a> (DPML) and licenced under the commercially friendly 
        <a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0">Apache Software Licence V2.0.</a>
        You may not use these distributions except in compliance with the License.
        Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed 
        under the  License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT  WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS 
        OF ANY KIND, either  express  or implied. See the License for the specific language 
        governing permissions and limitations under the License.
      </p>

      </subsection>

      <table>
        <tr><th>Platform</th><th>Binary</th><th>MD5</th><!--<th>ASC</th>--></tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Windows</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://download.dpml.net/milestones/depot/@DEPOT-PRODUCT-VERSION@/dpml-depot-win32-@DEPOT-PRODUCT-VERSION@.zip">
              dpml-depot-win32-@DEPOT-PRODUCT-VERSION@.zip</a>
          </td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://download.dpml.net/milestones/depot/@DEPOT-PRODUCT-VERSION@/dpml-depot-win32-@DEPOT-PRODUCT-VERSION@.md5">MD5</a>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Linux</td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://download.dpml.net/milestones/depot/@DEPOT-PRODUCT-VERSION@/dpml-depot-linux-@DEPOT-PRODUCT-VERSION@.tar.gz">
              dpml-depot-linux-@DEPOT-PRODUCT-VERSION@.tar.gz</a>
          </td>
          <td>
            <a href="http://download.dpml.net/milestones/depot/@DEPOT-PRODUCT-VERSION@/dpml-depot-linux-@DEPOT-PRODUCT-VERSION@.md5">MD5</a>
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>

    </section>

    <section name="Prerequisite Products">

      <subsection name="Java JDK @JAVA-PRODUCT-VERSION@">

        <p>
        Products and tutorials included under this site require the installation of 
        Java @JAVA-PRODUCT-VERSION@ or later.  General speaking this means you need to install
        the <a href="@JAVA-DOWNLOAD-URL@">Java @JAVA-PRODUCT-VERSION@ SDK</a> for development 
        purposes.  If your needs are limited to runtime solutions you may want to install 
        just the Java @JAVA-PRODUCT-VERSION@ JRE (also included within the JDK).
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Ant @ANT-PRODUCT-VERSION@">

        <p>
        Magic is an Ant extension library (antlib).  To fucntion correctly
        you need to install the Ant @ANT-PRODUCT-VERSION@ binary distribution.
        </p>

      </subsection>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>

