<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="mcconnell@osm.net">Stephen McConnell</author>
    <title>Resource Management</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Transit Artifacts">

      <subsection name="Tutorial Objective">

        <p>
        The aim of this tutorial is to establish a good understanding 
        of the term "artifact", the structure of an artifact URI, an the 
        role of the Transit system concerning resource retrieval, hosts,
        and resource caching.
        </p>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Definition of an Artifact">

        <p>
        An artifact is any streamable resource locatable using the <code>artifact</code>
        URL protocol.  Examples of resources include - jar files, property files, XML 
        files, files containing meta data, serialized objects, images, etc.  Resources 
        can be viewed as artifacts if they can be located using the <code>artifact</code>
        protocol. The protocol structure is as follows:
        </p>

        <code>artifact:[type]:[group]/[name]#[version]</code>

        <p>
        To locate a resource Transit maps the <code>[type], [group], 
        [name],</code> and <code>[version]</code> fields of the artifact URI to a URL
        using a layout assigned to a particular host defintion.  The most common layout 
        strategy (refered to as the classic layout) maps the artifact specifications 
        according to the following rule:
        </p>

        <code>[host-address]/[group]/[type]s/[name]-[version].[type]</code>

        <p>
        The eclipse layout maps artifacts in accordance with the following scheme:
        </p>

        <code>[host-address]/[group]-[version]/[name].[type]</code>

        <p>
        In addition to the above you can create and declare a custom layout handler
        via the Transit Management API via <code>net.dpml.transit.model.LayoutRegistryModel</code>.
        </p>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Using Artifacts">

        <p> 
        The following testcase demonstrates the use of an artifact to retrieve a property 
        file from a remote location and supply it as an input stream to a Properties object.
        The initial <code>setUp()</code> method handles the declaration of the Artifact protocol handler 
        to the JVM.  This is Transit's hook into the JVM's URL Hander object model.  Within the 
        <code>testPropertyLoading()</code> we construct a new URL using an artifact specification
        that declares a resource type of "properties", a group named "dpml/test", the name 
        "example-property-file" and a version equal to "2.2".  We then pass the URLs resource 
        stream to a new Property instance and print out the value of a property declared in the 
        properties resource.
        </p>

        <p><i>Source:</i> <tt>trunk/validation/resources/src/test/net/osm/tutorial/TransitTestCase.java</tt></p>
        <source>
public class TransitTestCase extends TestCase
{
    protected void setUp() throws Exception
    {
        System.setProperty( "java.protocol.handler.pkgs", "net.dpml.transit" );
    }

    public void testPropertyLoading() throws Exception
    {
        URL url = new URL( "artifact:properties:dpml/test/example-property-file#2.2" );
        InputStream input = url.openStream();
        Properties properties = new Properties();
        properties.load( input );
        String message = properties.getProperty( "tutorial.message" );
        System.out.println( message );
    }
}</source>
        <p>
        Testcase output:
        </p>
<pre>  [x:junit] Executing forked test.
  [x:junit] Running net.osm.tutorial.TransitTestCase
  [x:junit] Welcome to the world of Transit!
  [x:junit] Tests run: 1, Failures: 0, Errors: 0, Time elapsed: 0.344 sec</pre>


      </subsection>


      <subsection name="Behind the Scenes">

        <p>
        When the new URL constructor is invoked the JVM checks available URLStreamHandlers
        using a number of mechanisms - one of which is to check the value of the 
        "java.protocol.handler.pkgs" system property.  The JVM will look for a protocol
        handler named "net.dpml.transit" + [protocol].Handler.  The Transit's artifact
        Handler class is primarily responsible for the establishment of a ArtifactURLConnection.
        The ArtifactURLConnection holds a reference to the Transit system.  When the openStream
        operation is invoked the Artifact URL connection will use a cache handler to resolve
        the URL to a local cached resource.  The cache handler will check prioritized hosts for 
        the resource (converting the artifact to the appropriate URL for the host as it evaluates
        potential multiple candidates).  When a host is located a network service downloads the 
        resource to the local cache (itself equivalent to a local files based repository). The 
        openStream() request is then delegated to the local resource.
        </p>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Key Benefits">

        <ul>
          <li>Removal of "location" concerns from the codebase.</li>
          <li>Notion of transport protocol is abstracted out.</li>
          <li>Potential redundancy when a resource exists on multiple hosts.</li>
          <li>Configuration concerns are separted from usage.</li>
          <li>Artifact structure encorages consistent naming patterns and resource versioning.</li>
          <li>Functionlity is encapsulated with the URL and URLConnection object model.</li>
        </ul>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Next Topic - Plugins">
      
        <p>
        This page has presented a more in-depth look at the <tt>artifact</tt> protocol.
        The <a href="plugins.html">next tutorial</a> introduced a simple datatype called a 
        <tt>part</tt> that describes an object instantiation strategy with a classloader 
        chain definition.  This datatype is commonly referred to as a <tt>plugin</tt> and 
        demonstrates the usage of one artifact to describe the usage of many artifacts.
        </p>

      </subsection>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>

