<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="mcconnell@osm.net">Stephen McConnell</author>
    <title>Resource Management</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Transit Repository Tutorial">

      <subsection name="Tutorial Objectives">

        <p>
        The objective of this tutorial is to introduce the concept of a resource 
        respository, to describe the role of local and remote repositories in the 
        Transit system, and to show examples of definition and setup of a private 
        repository.
        </p>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="What is a Repository?">

        <p>
        A repository is a resource server.  Examples of repositories include 
        the HTTP based DPML Repository accessible under 
        <a href="http://repository.dpml.net/classic/">http://repository.dpml.net/classic</a>.
        Techically this is simply a web server with content structured in terms of groups
        and resources named using a particular convention.  The mapping between an artifact
        uri and a repository is handled by a Layout object that is declared as part of a 
        resource host definition.  A layout implementation translates the artifact uri to
        to a url relative to the target host structure.  Using this model Transit can provide
        suport for varying repository access and transport strategies.
        </p>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="Creating a repository">

        <p>
        Transit's default ResourceHost implementation provides out of the box support 
        for file, http and ftp based respository access.  The simplest way to create a new 
        repository is to setup a file based repository.  This simply involves the the creation
        of the repository root directory, adding a group directory under the root, adding 
        a directory named after the content type under the group directory, then adding 
        your resources into the type directories using the naming convention [name]-[version].[type]
        or [name].[type] in the case of artifacts without a version.  You host defintion 
        simply references the root directory using the file: protocol as the repository base 
        directory.  Note - the above description is based on the 'classic' layout strategy
        used across the majority of know repositories and internally within Transit's local 
        cache.
        </p>

        <p>
        A more typical scenario is the establishment of a company wide repository within a 
        local intranet.  For this you need to setup a server (e.g. HTTP) with a file based 
        resource handler then configure Transit by declaring a new remote host and defintining 
        the host base url as the http server.
        </p>

        <p>
        The following commandline operations demonstrate the setup of a new local repository
        using a file protocol referencing a root repository directory of <tt>${dpml.data}/demo</tt>.
        Symbolic expressions used within the host defintion may include any system property and
        core Transit location references (such as <tt>${dpml.home}</tt>).
        </p>

<pre>
$ transit add host demo -url file:${dpml.data}/demo -priority 60
</pre>

        <p>
        Once created the new repository can be listed using the following command:
        </p>

<pre>
$ transit info
</pre>

      </subsection>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>

