<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="mcconnell@osm.net">Stephen McConnell</author>
    <title>Component Development Strategies</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Training Material Index ">

      <p>
      The OSM Tutorials are provided with the aim of getting you up and operational
      as quickly as possible.  The tutorials are loosly related to the DPML products
      Transit, Depot, Metro, and the Station server management platform - each 
      representing a specific concern in Java based component development and 
      application delivery.
      </p>

      <p>
      The tutorial assumes you have <a href="../download/index.html">downloaded</a> 
      and installed a JDK and the DPML SDK.
      </p>

      <table>
        <tr><th>Subject</th><th>Description</th></tr>
        <tr>
          <td><a href="resources/index.html">Resource Management</a></td>
          <td>
            This tutorial introduces the Transit resource managment system
            and takes you though examples of how you can improve your code by 
            eliminating resource location and retrival concerns.  
            The tutorial also present strategies concerning classloader 
            construction, classloader chains, and plugin management solutions.
            This material will be of particular interest to developers and architects 
            dealing with dynamically adaptive or runtime evolvable systems. This 
            material is to some extent optional as is deals with the a general but 
            low-level concern - however, a read through is recommended.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><a href="tooling/index.html">Development Tooling</a></td>
          <td>
            This tutorial focusses on the establishment of a production build 
            environment using technologies that provide transitive dependency 
            management.  The tutorial presents the general setup of a build 
            environment, examples of projects representing typical development 
            needs, examples of the use of transitive dependencies in development
            and the generation of project data and runtime information.  Readers 
            will gain an understanding of the concerns related to build configuration,
            centralization of project information, strategies concerning test automation, 
            and approaches to content publication and version management.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><a href="components/index.html">Component Development</a></td>
          <td>
            This tutorial is about the development of components using the 
            IOC (Inversion of Control) principal.  The tutorial takes you though the 
            development, testing, and management of component solutions using the 
            DPML Metro container.  It presents a series of 
            examples dealing with context driven IOC of simple though to complex 
            composite components and strategies supporting effective component 
            reuse.  Feel free to start on this tutorial as it delivers the most 
            value in terms of potential development productivity.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><a href="applications/index.html">Application Management</a></td>
          <td>
            This tutorial is primarily concerned with the management of deployed 
            applications. However, developers will find this material valuable relative
            to its coverage of remote component management of application clusters.
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>

    
    </section>

  </body>
</document>

