<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="mcconnell@osm.net">Stephen McConnell</author>
    <title>Component Development Strategies</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Training Material Index ">

      <p>
      The OSM Tutorials are provided with the aim of getting you and operational
      as quickly as possible.  The tutorials are loosly related to the DPML products
      Transit, Magic, Depot, and Metro - each representing a specific concern in 
      Java based component development and application deivery.
      </p>

      <p>
      The tutorial assumes you have already <a href="../download/index.html">downloaded</a> 
      and <a href="../download/setup/index.html">installed</a> Depot and 
      prerequise products (JDK and Ant build system). 
      </p>

      <table>
        <tr><th>Subject</th><th>Description</th></tr>
        <tr>
          <td><a href="resources/index.html">Resource Management</a></td>
          <td>
            This tutorial introduces the Transit resource managment system
            and takes you though examples of how you can improve your code by 
            eliminating resource location and retrival concerns from you development
            code.  The tutorial also present strategies concerning classloader 
            construction, classloader chains, and plugin management solutions.
            This material will be of particular interest to developers and architects 
            dealing with dynamically adaptive or runtime evolvable systems. This 
            material is to some exent optional as is deals with the a general but 
            low-level concern - however, a quick read through of the introductory
            page is recommended.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><a href="tooling/index.html">Development Tooling</a></td>
          <td>
            This tutorial focusses on the establishment of a production build 
            environment using technologies that provide transitive dependency 
            management.  The tutorial presents the general setup of a build 
            environment, examples of projects representing typical development 
            needs, examples of the use of transitive dependencies in development
            and the generation of project data and runtime information.  Readers 
            planning on getting into component development should go thought this 
            material and personal interested in capturaturing project metrics 
            and related quality assurance concerns could going some interesting 
            milage.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><a href="components/index.html">Component Development</a></td>
          <td>
            This tutorial is all about the development of components using the 
            IOC (Inversion of Control) principal.  The tutorial takes you though the 
            development, testing, and management of component solutions using the 
            DPML Metro component management solution.  It presents a series of 
            examples dealing with context driven IOC of simple though to complex 
            composite components and stretegies supporting effective component 
            reuse.  Feel free to kick off on this tutorial as it delivers the most 
            value in terms of potential development productivity.
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td><a href="applications/index.html">Application Management</a></td>
          <td>
            This tutorial is primarily concerned with the management of deployed 
            applications. However, developers will find this material valuable relative
            to its coverage of configuration management and instalation services. 
            Product support personel will be more interested in Depot managenent aspects
            and the potential for applying Depot as an application delivery vehicle.
          </td>
        </tr>
      </table>

    
    </section>

  </body>
</document>

